DAN KLEIN: Today, we'll be talking
about reinforcement learning.
Reinforcement learning has a long
history, including in the area of
animal reinforcement learning, for
example, in psychology and behavioral
psychology.
And people have thought long and hard
about what could the mechanisms be by
which, based on feedback from our
actions and our environment, we learn
how to act over time.
And today, we'll talk about how we might
operationalize some of these
ideas in code.
Here's the schematic for
reinforcement learning.
The basic idea is you have an agent
who is acting as always.
So the agent has actions available
to it and chooses an action.
The environment then does what it always
does, which is it resolves in
some way that's not entirely
determined by the action.
For example, there may be some
nondeterminism or uncertainty.
When the action resolves, what the agent
receives back is two things.
One is a reward that could be kind of
a bonus or a penalty, and these are
the things we want to learn
to maximize over time.
The other thing the agent receives in
response to its actions is a percept.
We see what happens.
So we get a state back in the
simplest formulation.
Later on, we'll see how
we can relax this.
But for now, we take an action which
we essentially submit to the
environment by doing it, and the
environment returns to us a state,
which is the result, and a reward,
which we want to maximize.
We
Want to act to maximize our rewards, but
of course, we have to learn to do
that, because in this setting, we won't
know what actions will produce
rewards until we try them.
Because we're actually trying things
in the environment, all of the
learning, all of the ways we have
available to us to make good decisions
are mediated by what we experience
which are samples of outcomes.
When you take an action,
you see what happens.
But you don't see everything
that might have happened.
So let's see some examples of
what this can actually do.
This first example is from Peter
Stone's group at UT Austin.
And the story here is they have
these AIBOs that play soccer.
And of course, every match is in a
different stadium, they go on their
world tour.
And when you're a soccer playing AIBO,
at least if you're on this team, you
have this ritual.
At the beginning of every match, you go
to this new stadium and you have to
learn how to walk again because the
surface is a little bit different.
You get a different vibe
from the crowd.
It changes everything.
So let's see what happens.
The robots are not just
flailing around.
They have a gait that's programmed
that allows them to walk.
But on a new surface, it initially
does something like this.
It does what you think-- one leg moves
and the opposite back leg moves.
And it more or less makes progress in
the direction that it's trying to go.
As this is happening, it collects
information through a camera that
shows what's actually going on.
Is it making forward progress?
Is the world shaking left to right
because it's unstable?
It then continues training which
essentially boils down to trying
variations and learning responses
based on what it's seeing.
During training, it looks a little
bit like this which is better.
They let these AIBOs walk back and forth
along this new floor until this
process completes.
And when this process completes,
you have this.
You have the ninja dog.
It's amazingly smooth.
And then they go and they crush their
competition and all that.
In this particular case, not only do
you move faster, but it's important
for how these soccer playing robots work
that the camera, the vision they
have not shake around like crazy.
That makes it very hard to figure
out what's going on.
You think the ball's kind of
shaking through the air.
No, you're shaking.
Right?
So in addition to trying to go fast, the
reward signal also should include
something about going stably.
And that's all mixed together here.
Here's another example.
People wondered how you might be able
to learn to walk in a way that's
partially mediated by the
structure, right?
You've been given this body that has
joints in places that work for
walking, and also based on some
experiences you have.
And this is Russ Tedrake's group at MIT,
and here is essentially a toddler
robot learning to walk.
Let's take a look.
So at the beginning, it kind of wobbles
back and forth and maybe it's
making forward-- no--
backward progress.
And maybe it should wobble
a little harder.
Maybe that'll work.
And then over time, it starts
kind of moving in a not
entirely straight line.
And then the next thing you know, it's
moving purposefully around the room in
a pretty straight line.
And before you know it,
it's off to college.
So that's a case of, again, trying
various actions, seeing what's
working, improving those through
interactions with the environment.
You're actually going to get a chance to
do this as well which is I'm going
to show you today a crawler robot.
It's not quite as complex as these other
robots, but if you squint, it's
basically there.
It's got two joints, and the goal
is for it to learn to walk.
You'll build this in your
project threes.
Actually, let's see an
example right now.
OK, so here, what do we see?
We see a crawler robot.
Its goal, in case you can't tell because
it's kind of inept right now,
is to move to the right.
Whenever it moves to the right, it
receives a reward of plus one.
Whenever it moves to the left, it
receives a reward of minus one.
And its goal is to over time
maximize its rewards.
So it should tend to move
right over time.
Problem is, it doesn't exactly know what
actions make it move right and
thereby give it rewards.
And it's trickier than you might think,
because in order to move right,
you have to spend some time not moving
at all as you reset your arm.
There are some controls here
I'll tell you about later.
But essentially, it's kind
of figuring it out.
And if I skip a lot of time,
it's going, right?
It's off to college.
OK.
So you guys will get to build that.
How was all of this done?
The framework we're going to work
in is reinforcement learning.
In reinforcement learning formally, we
still imagine that there is a Markov
decision process.
So just like the MDPs
we've seen before.
And we already saw that in
the general diagram.
We take actions and there is some state
and reward that comes back, but
it's not entirely deterministic.
So it's just an MDP.
There's still a set of states.
There are still a set of actions which
might depend on the state we're in.
And there's still some kind of model in
principle that is determining which
state results and rewards we get back.
And there's still a reward function
associated with the outcomes.
We're still trying to learn a policy
which is essentially figuring out how
we should act in a given state.
The new twist in reinforcement learning
and what makes this so much
harder than just solving an
MDP is that we do not know
the transition function.
We don't know the rewards.
And that is even though based on my
state and my action, there's a certain
set of outcomes with a certain
probability distribution.
I don't know which probability
distribution it is.
And so the only way to really know
what our actions do and where the
rewards come from is to try things out,
and then learn from our samples
that we experience.
Now, of course, because we're trying
things out from a state of partial
information, we're going
to make some mistakes.
And so there is always going to be this
process of trying things out not
all of which work optimally.
So here's an MDP.
This is, again, the race car.
You see the three states
of the race car.
And if I gave you this MDP,
you could just solve it.
You could value iteration or
expectimax for that matter.
If you were going to reinforcement learn
how to be this car that tries
not to overeat, the difference would be
you still know whether you're cool,
warm, or overheated, and you still know
that you can move fast or slow.
What you don't know is what
fast and slow do.
So for all you know, fast is the
best idea ever, or slow is
the best idea ever.
You try some things, maybe you end up
going too slow or maybe you overheat.
And you have to try things again and
slowly learn what these actions do
from each state.
A critical difference, now that we're
thinking about reinforcement learning,
is the difference between what we're
doing now and what we were doing in
the last unit on solving Markov decision
processes, especially since
even in reinforcement learning, there
are still all of these MDP-like things
like rewards and so on.
Offline solution is when you know what
your actions will do, and in
computation, in simulation, in your
head, you think about consequences,
whether that's via an expectimax
style search or a dynamic
program like value iteration.
You realize that jumping into the pit is
a bad idea because you know it has
a negative reward, and so you
never actually do it.
That's offline solution.
When you're doing online learning, you
have to actually jump into the pit
before you know it is bad.
You might imagine that over time, this
increases the cost of the robots.